Finding Aid for [Published works of John Harvey Kellogg including books, pamphlets, and periodicals], 1874-1953
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Pamphlets
  - "A new method for the radical treatment or femoral hernia," (reprinted from Transactions of the Michigan State Medical Society June 1896 ) (Box 7)
  - "A new method of operating or hemorrhoids," (reprinted from Bacteriological World and Modern Medicine February 1892 ) (Box 7)
  - "A now procedure for suspension of the pelvic colon," (reprinted from American Journal of Surgery April 1917 ) (Box 7)
  - "The non-surgical treatment of ovarian diseases," (reprinted from Modern Medicine and Bacteriological Review 1893 ) (Box 7)
  - "The non-surgical treatment of the pelvic disorders of women," (reprinted Transactions of the Michigan State Medical Society June 1896 ) (Box 7)
  - "Normal colon habits," (reprinted from Irving Fisher and Haven Emerson, How to Live (20th ed. New York 1938 ) (Box 7)
  - "Observations on the relations of posture to health and a new method of studying posture and development," (reprinted from Bulletin of the Battle Creek Sanitarium and Hospital Clinic September 1927 ) (Box 7)
  - "An oculo-neurological fad," (reprinted from Modern Medicine and Bacteriological Review December 1894 ) (Box 7)
  - "Outline studies of the human figure, 2nd ed," (Battle Creek undated ) (Box 7)
  - "Oxygen enemata," (reprinted from The Therapeutic Gazette September 15, 1887 ) (Box 7)
  - "Oxygen enemata as a remedy in certain diseases of the liver and intes tinal tract," (reprinted from Journal of the American Medical Association August 25, 1888 ) (Box 7)
  - "Outline of the Organization of Christian Help Bands," (n.p. undated ) (Box 7)
  - "The paraffin treatment of constipation," (reprinted from New York Medical Journal September 12, 1914 ) (Box 8)
  - "A perfectly aseptic drainage-tube," (reprinted from Modern Medicine and Bacteriological Review, 1895 ) (Box 8)
  - "Pernicious packing-house piffle," (reprinted from Good Health, April 1931 ) (Box 8)
  - "Pernicious piffle," (reprinted from Good Health, July 1922 ) (Box 8)
  - "The philosophy of getting well." (n.p., c1882) (Box 8)
  - "Phototherapy in chronic diseases," (reprinted from The Journal of Advanced Therapeutics, February 1905 ) (Box 8)
  - "Physical coefficients," (reprinted from Modern Medicine and Bacteriological Review, July 1895 ) (Box 8)
  - "Physical deterioration resulting from school life: causes; remedy." (n.p., c1896) (Box 8)
  - "The physical effects of alcohol and tobacco." (Battle Creek, c1882) (Box 8)
  - "Plication of the hernial sac in operating for femoral hernia," (reprinted from American Journal of Surgery, New Series, undated ) (Box 8)
  - "Poison bullets," (reprinted from Good Health, November 1917 ) (Box 8)
  - "Pork, or the dangers of pork-eating exposed." (Battle Creek 1897 ) (Box 8)
  - "Practical suggestions respecting the ventilation of buildings," (reprinted from Report of the Michigan State Board of Health, 1891 ) (Box 8)
  - "Progress in dietetics. Two new cereal foods," (reprinted from Good Health undated ) (Box 8)
  - "Prohibition not a failure," (reprinted from Good Health, March 1923 ) (Box 8)
  - "Prolapsed colon," (reprinted from Modern Medicine, November 1893 ) (Box 8)
  - "Pyorrhea a meat eater's disorder." (n.p. undated ) (Box 8)
  - "Pythagoras on the ethics of diet." (Battle Creek 1928 ) (Box 8)
  - "The radical cure of retro-displacements of the uterus and procidentia by Alexander's operation and median colporrhaphy," (reprinted from Transactions of the Michigan State Medical Society, 1887 ) (Box 8)
  - "Rational gynecology," (reprinted from The Medical News, December 18, 1897 ) (Box 8)
  - "Rational physical therapy," (reprinted from Physical Therapeutics, undated ) (Box 8)
  - "Rational 'rest-cure'," (reprinted from Modern Medicine, November 1893 ) (Box 8)
  - "The rational treatment of consumption," (reprinted from Detroit Lancet, July 1882 ) (Box 8)
  - "Recent statistics of heart disease, with special reference to its increasing incidence," (reprinted from Journal of the American Medical Association, May 15, 1920 ) (Box 8)
  - "Relation of diet to dental caries and mouth infection." (n.p., c1915) (Box 8)
  - "Relation of habits to life expectancy," (reprinted from Good Health, 1918 ) (Box 8)
  - "The relation of intestinal bacteria to human welfare." (n.r. undated ) (Box 8)
  - "The perfected posture chair," (reprinted from Good Health, December 1930 ) (Box 8)
  - "Relation of preventable sickness to taxation," (reprinted from Report of the Michigan State Board of Health, 1880 ) (Box 8)
  - "Relation of public health to race degeneracy," (reprinted from American Journal of Public Health, c1913 ) (Box 8)
  - "The relation of recent bacteriological studies to the etiology of typhoid fever." (n.p., c1893) (Box 8)
  - "The relation of static disturbances of the abdominal viscera to displacements of the pelvic organs," (reprinted from Proceedings of the International Periodical Congress of Gynecology and Obstetrics, 1892 ) (Box 8)
  - "The relation of the chemistry and bacteriology of the stomach to dental caries," (reprinted from Dental Register, c 1897 ) (Box 8)
  - "A renal calculus of unusual size. Nephrectomy -- recovery," (reprinted from Bacteriological World and Modern Medicine, September 1892 ) (Box 8)
  - "Report on twelve cases of Alexander's operation," (reprinted from Journal of the American Medical Association, August ?0, 1887 ) (Box 8)
  - "Report of twenty-five cases of Alexander's operation," (reprinted from Annals of Gynecology, December 1887 ) (Box 8)
  - "Report of forty-eight cases of Alexander's operation," (reprinted from Journal of the American Medical Association, December 8, 1888 ) (Box 8)
  - "Report of sixty-three cases of Alexander's operation," (reprinted from Transactions of the American Association of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, September 1888 ) (Box 8)
  - "Report of seventy-three cases of Alexander's operation for shortening the round ligaments, and description of an improved method of operation," (reprinted from Proceedings of the Michigan State Medical Society, 1889 ) (Box 8)
  - "Report of fifty-two consecutive cases of ovariotomy, including two of hysterectomy," (reprinted from Transactions of the Michigan State Medical Society, 1890 ) (Box 8)
  - "Report of the sanitarium hospital, Battle Creek, Mich., 1889-1891" (reprinted from Bacteriological World and Modern Medicine, February 1892 ) (Box 8)
  - "The results obtained by use of diphtheria antitoxin," (reprinted from Proceedings of the Third Annual Conference of Health Officers in Michigan, 1896 ) (Box 8)
  - "Rhubarb a poison food," (reprinted from Good Health, May 1917 ) (Box 8)
  - "Les romans. Cinquieme mille." (Bale 1892 ) (Box 8)
  - "Rules for right living."
    - (Battle Creek 1935 ) (Box 8)
    - (Battle Creek 1947 [two different copies]) (Box 8)
  - "Safety methods in the care of surgical patients," (from American Journal of Surgery October 1920 ) (Box 8)
  - "Sanitarium methods," (reprinted from Bacteriological World and Modern Medicine, March 1892 ) (Box 8)
  - "The 'sanitarium method' of dealing with chronic invalids," (reprinted from Journal of the American Medical Association, September 19, 1806 ) (Box 8)
  - "Sanitary associations," (reprinted from Report of the Michigan State Board of Health, 1879 ) (Box 8)
  - "A series of exercises, based upon the system of Ling..." (Battle Creek, 1891 ) (Box 8)
  - "Shortening the round ligaments vs. ventral fixation for tetroversion," (reprinted from Modern Medicine and Bacteriological Review, May 1894 ) (Box 8)
  - "Should an athlete eat meat?" (Battle Creek, c1928) (Box 8)
  - "Should the colon be sacrificed or May it be reformed?," (reprinted from Journal of the American Medical Association June 30, 1917 ) (Box 8)
  - "The simple life in a nutshell," (Battle Creek, n.d.[three different editions, none with dates]) (Box 8)
  - "A simple method of approximating the proper ration for a diabetic patient," (reprinted from Journal of the American Medical Association, September 1923 ) (Box 8)
  - "A simple method of shortening the round ligaments of the uterus for the cure of retroversion," (reprinted from Medical Record, April 22, 1916 ) (Box 8)
  - "Sit up-don't sit down: the perfect chair at last," (reprinted from Good Health, November 1931 ) (Box 8)
  - "Report of sixty cases of uterine myomata treated by electrolysis, with descriptions of new forms of electrodes and a coulombmeter," (reprinted The Times and Register, February 7, 1891 ) (Box 8)
  - "The smoker's heart," (Battle Creek undated ) (Box 8)
  - "The smoker's liver." (Battle Creek, n.d.) (Box 8)
  - "Something every hospital needs," (reprinted from Hospital Management, February 1924 ) (Box 8)
  - "Soybeans as human food," (Battle Creek, c 1930 ) (Box 8)
  - "Special health values of the soybean," 1937 ) (Box 8)
  - "Special gymnastics for the treatment of spinal curvature," (Battle Creek 1897 ) (Box 8)
  - "Special sanitariums for the treatment of disorders of the stomach," (reprinted from Modern Medicine, May 1897 ) (Box 8)
  - "Stefansson's tallow-eating stunt," (reprinted from Good Health, August 1929 ) (Box 8)
  - "A study of the mechanism of gastric contractions," (reprinted from the special issue of the Bulletin of the Battle Creek Sanitarium and Hospital Clinic, October 1929 ) (Box 8)
  - "Suggestions toward checking race degeneracy due to the condition of school life," (reprinted from Hygiene and Physical Education, May-July 1909 [two different issues]) (Box 8)
  - "Summary of my personal experience with electrolysis in the treatment of fibroid tumors," (reprinted from The Times and Register, November 21, 1891 ) (Box 8)
  - "Sunlight," (reprinted from Welfare, October 1927 ) (Box 8)
  - "The supreme importance of clean, uncooked milk for infants and children and the defects of pasteurized milk," (reprinted from Good Health, August 1921 ) (Box 8)
  - "Surgery of the ileocecal valve," (reprinted from Surgery, Gynaecology and Obstetrics, November 1918 ) (Box 8)
  - "The surgical treatment of retroversion of the uterus," (reprinted from Bacteriological World and Modern Medicine, August 1892 ) (Box 8)
  - "Technic of operation for repair of the ileocecal valve, with summary of the results in a series of twenty-six operations," (reprinted from Annals of Surgery, January 1918 ) (Box 8)
  - "Ten old arguments for flesh-eating answered by modern science." (n.p. undated ) (Box 8)
  - "Tendencies toward race degeneracy,"
    - ([copy 1] (reprinted from New York Medical Journal, September 9, 1911 ) (Box 8)
    - ([copy 2] Senate document no. 648, 62nd Congress, 2nd Session. Washington, D.C. 1912 ) (Box 8)
  - "Treatment of colitis by changing the intestinal flora," (reprinted from Bulletin of the Battle Creek Sanitarium And Hospital Clinic, January 1928 ) (Box 8)
  - "Treatment of constipation," (reprinted from Medical Journal and Record, August 18, 1926 ) (Box 8)
  - "The truth about alcohol as a medicine." (Battle Creek 1906 ) (Box 8)
  - "The truth about fasting," (reprinted from Modern Medicine, September 1908 ) (Box 8)
  - "Tuberculosis. Relation of the disease in the milk and flesh of animals to the same malady in human beings," (reprinted from Proceedings of the National Livestock Sanitary Convention, 1894 ) (Box 8)
  - "The turkey buzzard's liver," (reprinted from Good Health, May 1919 ) (Box 8)
  - "Two new electrodes," (reprinted from The Times and Register, November 14, 1891 ) (Box 8)
  - "Two new fundamental laws of cerebral function, 2nd American ed." (Battle Creek undated ) (Box 8)
  - "The uses of water in health and disease. A practical treatise on the bath, its history and uses." (Battle Creek 1876 ) (Box 8)
  - "The value of exercise as a therapeutic means in the treatment of the pelvic diseases of women," (reprinted from Transactions of the American Association of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, September 1890 ) (Box 8)
  - "The value of strength tests in the prescription of exercise." (Battle Creek 1896 ) (Box 8)
    (two different issues)
  - "Vegetarianism: The kindly fruits of the earth," (reprinted from The Arbitrator, February 1920 ) (Box 8)
  - "Ventilation," (reprinted from Report of the Michigan State Board of Health, 1884 ) (Box 8)
  - "What is biologic living?," (reprinted from Good Health, September 1929 ) (Box 8)
  - "What is the matter with the American stomach?" (Battle Creek 1896 [two different issues]) (Box 8)
  - "What scientific men say about meat and meat eating." (Battle Creek, c1928) (Box 8)
  - "What's the matter with our schools?" (Battle Creek, c1923) (Box 8)
  - "Why does your head ache?," (reprinted from Good Health, undated ) (Box 8)
  - "Why the athlete does not smoke." (Battle Creek undated ) (Box 8)
  - "Why we should eat more potatoes," (reprinted from American Potato Journal June 1929 ) (Box 8)
  - "The world's greatest authorities pronounce meat unnecessary." (Battle Creek, c1928) (Box 8)
  - "The world's greatest problem. An address to the students of Battle Creek College." (n.p. undated ) (Box 8)
  - "Your body comes first," (reprinted from The Magazine of Michigan, March 1930 ) (Box 8)
  - "City medical missions," (reprinted from Medical Missionary, March-June 1898 ) (Box 8)
  - "Diet helps for doctors." (Battle Creek 1928 ) (Box 8)
  - "Directions for making a personal health survey" and "Personal health survey" undated ), typescripts (Box 8)
  - "The Third Race Betterment Conference to be held at Battle Creek (Box 8)
  - Michigan January 2 to 6, 1928." (Battle Creek 1927? by Ella Eaton Kellogg:) (Box 8)
  - "Natural food recipes," (Battle Creek undated ) (Box 8)
  - "Cooking school for instruction in Mrs. Dr. Kellogg's system of scientific cookery." (Battle Creek 1889 ) (Box 8)
- Serials
  - The Cricket. (Box 9)
    - Vol. 1, no.1-10 May 1898-June 1899 (Box 9)
  - The Health Reformer., 1866-
    - Vols. 1-12 1866-1877 (Box 9)
  - Good Health. A Journal of Hygiene, 1878-
    (continuation of The Health Reformer)
    - Vols. 14 -- 23 1879-1888 (Box 9)
      (wanting Vols. 13, 17, 21)
    - Vols. 24 -- 32 1889-1897 (Box 10)
    - Vols. 33 -- 44 1898-1909 (Box 11)
    - Vols. 45 -- 54 1910-1919 (Box 12)
    - Vols. 55 -- 64 1920-1929 (Box 13)
    - Vols. 65 -- 74 1930-1939 (Box 14)
    - Vols. 75 -- 88 1940-1953 (Box 15)